I patreon subscribers welcome and thanks
for your support many of you voted to
have me address sympathy and empathy
from an evolutionary perspective I think
it's an excellent choice the topic is
one of my favorites and it couldn't
possibly be more important at this
moment in history I'm not going to
attempt to define these terms
etymologically to say how they came into
usage in what they have meant in the
past my purpose here is to define them
for maximum value for that to be
achieved the two have to be defined
precisely such that they interact in a
way to cover the territory to maximum
effect let's talk a bit about adaptive
evolution we all tend to think of
evolution as about the past and indeed
there's good reason for that
but adaptive evolution occurs because it
prepares creatures to deal with future
environments the past cannot be changed
the future is where one's profits can be
enhanced and ones cost can be reduced
and so that's what evolution is about
when we think about sympathy and empathy
it would be good for us to think about
them in that context let's start with
empathy human beings are very special
creatures far beyond any other creature
that has existed if we are programmed by
experiences that we have after we are
born one result of that is that one
human being and another may differ to a
great degree and this means that the
range of behavior may be quite wide at
the same time we are very highly social
creatures which means that our success
as human beings is largely dictated by
how well we interface with others of our
kind so in order to do that well it is
very valuable to be able to predict what
other people are going to think what
they will feel and ultimately what they
are going to do in response to changes
in their circumstances empathy is the
very special evolved tool that we use to
figure out what other people are going
to do in response to changes in their
circumstance so if I'm to talk about
empathizing with you in order to
empathize with you I run the data of
your circumstance through my mind to see
how I would feel if I was in your shoes
if our minds are similar because we've
had similar developmental histories then
I may be very effective at this if our
minds are very different because we've
had very different developmental
trajectories then I may have nothing
more than a crude sketch it's still
probably better than nothing
but it's not going to be nearly as good
as if you and I have shared a great deal
of history the value of my empathy with
you however does not depend on whether
or not we're on the same team it is
important to understand one's enemies if
one is to defeat them just as it is
important to understand one's allies if
one is to aid them empathy does not pay
any heed to whether or not the person
that you are empathizing with is your
enemy or your ally now I've spoken so
far as if empathy is a general capacity
that two people have something like a
coefficient that dictates how well they
can empathize with each other and in
general that's probably true
there are certainly going to be places
though where two people can empathize to
a great degree but then fail in some
particular zone for example I grew up in
Los Angeles in the 1970s and 80s if I
meet somebody else who grew up under
similar circumstances in the same place
I may have a lot of insight into how
they're going to see the world but if
that person is female there may be some
set of circumstances or events that I
understand less well because they don't
mirror my own experience the same can be
said for generational differences if I
meet another biologist I may understand
a lot about how they see the world but
if that biologist is a baby boomer then
they grew up in boom times and and I did
not and that may affect the way we
understand each other it is also
possible to bootstrap empathy where one
does not share developmental
circumstances with somebody else
extensive contact between two people who
are dissimilar can result in coming to
understand how the other person sees the
world this may also be why human beings
are obsessed with narratives we love
movies and novels in large measure
because they run us through
circumstances that we will never face so
the
we can understand how characters in
those circumstances see the world and if
we ever run up against somebody who has
had a similar experience we may know a
great deal more about it than we would
otherwise scientific study can also
reveal such things behavioral scientists
in the last several decades have come to
understand that contrary to most of our
expectations
human beings often value a particular
opportunity not an absolute terms how
good is the opportunity but in relative
terms how good is that opportunity
relative to what other people have
knowing that allows us to correct for
one of our expectations all right now
let's talk about sympathy sympathy I
will argue is empathy plus alignment now
this fits the etymology sympathy same
pathos and what this means is that if I
empathize with somebody so that I know
the way in which they're likely to view
a particular circumstance and I also am
in alignment with them that is to say
they are on my team then my emotional
experience at their plight is liable to
be parallel to their emotional
experience so it makes intuitive sense
if I'm watching a film of an enemy of
mine and they are struggling to answer
questions from a hostile member of the
press well then I can appreciate that
they are feeling terror and maybe
embarrassment but my emotional
experience of watching them suffer
through these things may be one of
relief or even pleasure the German term
schadenfreude comes to mind meaning
pleasure that one takes at somebody
else's misfortune now if I'm watching a
friend of mine face the same
circumstance well then I am liable to
feel their terror and embarrassment
right along with them that would be
sympathy now some final thoughts many
things involve important kinds of
empathy and sympathy that we don't
typically associate with those terms
when musicians get together to play
music they have to understand what each
other are going to do in order to
interface in an effective way if they're
playing in front of an audience they
also have to figure out how the audience
is going to hear what's being played in
to be maximally effective the same can
be said for a humorist or an animator
and lastly educators face the situation
it is not enough to simply deliver
correct content and imagine that the
audience is going to understand it one
has to know how the audience is going to
hear what is being said so that they can
come to a new understanding of something
they didn't see before I hope this has
been useful I look forward to seeing
your comments and I also look forward to
next video